basically if you are a little bit out of
the loop what we did last time I
streamed was we made a game we are
cooking man we got 2 minutes left we're
already above 100K let's go and so what
we're going to do today is we're
actually going to continue on with that
game but we're going to slowly add more
platforms to it right um just as kind of
like an educational exercise really I
thought it would be fun to have a go
since rib actually supports quite a lot
of platforms including like web you know
my first time using Rib was that remake
for that game so obviously I haven't
tried it before so I thought we would
just give it a go and we'll see what
happens and hopefully it work out well
hopefully it won't be too difficult I
don't imagine it will be just because
our RB experience like thus far has been
pretty damn smooth so here's rib right
this is um you know we were using sea
lion uh last time they have a Wiki which
has working for web and so there's quite
a lot of things here so it can be
compiled to web assembly to run on web
compilation press is very similar to the
one used for deskt platforms with gtz
compiler but it requires a different
tool chain M script and SDK script
provides a set of tools to compile C
code to web assembly the main tool
provided is the EMCC compiler actually
direct replacement for GCC so anyone
with experience compiling code directly
in the command line should not have much
trouble cool okay so I don't know if
we'll be able to use cake for this um we
will see just cuz this is like it
provides an actual make file but since
it does should probably be okay um so
step one is to install the M script and
Tool chain so download inscript SDK
download a zip and decompress it to this
specific folder I love it when they like
tell you exactly which folder it needs
to be in all right yeah we got all the
things here so now I'm going to I'll
just use my terminal I think so we'll go
into this directory and then we're just
going to do emdk update awesome great
start okay well that is here I think it
might just be this is being weird thanks
po shell I didn't actually mean to use
this with Powershell um I just like
using terminal but um I could have just
not done Powershell I guess yeah Mr K
install latest so far it's gone pretty
well so we got a compile R withm
scripton okay here we here we go using
cmake so we can actually use cake that's
good set Rel web set up your own game so
avoid this Loop apparently I guess we'll
have a look at the templates and
everything and then use standard rib oh
so there's I guess two paths so what
would we do we would just yeah moving
all of your update and draw code to an
external function and then well I mean
we've got this here so we can probably
just look at what it means here so I'm
guessing instead of this Loop which is
not for web instead we do script and Set
uh main Loop and that's it and then
that's the function that just does that
so it's pretty straightforward so I
guess we'll do that I think we may
already have something similar in place
Yeah we actually do right so this
actually calls on update that's not
quite right cuz we actually need to put
all of this into like the loop so maybe
we'll make a new function here can
already set this up actually and we'll
call this like just I'll just call it
like Loop and then this will just be
Loop all right so we'll do activate
latest apparently so that just says like
some environment variables just
basically makes it your current kind of
working copy of incription so compile Ra
was next right so must be recompiled for
file generating sure make sure all parts
blah blah correctly configured MCC
should be accessible from the command
line so I guess we can try let me just
restart my command line uh and I'll just
I guess we can just open up a command
prompt or something and so if I type in
MCC awesome not recognized wow okay
great so well done the other thing that
did everything MRK I mean maybe I have
to call that or something didn't really
mention it I mean I would have thought
that like let's call activate latest
again we'll just see what it does here
we go path yeah it looks like it did set
it here yeah okay right so you have to
it sets it locally I guess well actually
shouldn't though it's in the path or is
that that's just the locally loaded path
in this shell I guess it is because if I
go to my environment variables yeah this
has nothing so yeah so it's not like a
it just does it temporarily so I guess
we just have to call activate latest or
whatever and maybe add that to our path
if we want it to be a bit more whatever
all right so to compile R directly from
the command line uh these are the
commands required to run I'm surprised
they don't have a specific file for this
like you have to execute all this stuff
manually it's a bit weird let's go to I
guess the location of this so to compile
ra directly from the command line these
are command to run so these are all rib
files right so where is rib like where
do we get that from I think we went into
the wiki right and then we had a look at
uh working anywhere with seake and then
I think yeah there's this seake list
that we got here can that build for the
web oh it can actually so maybe that
actually does it maybe this says oh here
we go web compiling for we subscription
and then you just do this oh beautiful I
think we've discovered what I was
looking for so I'm probably going to I
have to run this activate latest so now
we should have this y so EMC make we
should have and yes we do Okay cool so
let's run I guess this and then we just
run make okay no compatible generator
found please install ninja okay that's
fine I guess did it mention to install
ninja yet another build system there's
too many of these okay ninja. exe so if
I just pop that into my bin directory
maybe that will just work I just
downloaded ninja it comes
inside the zip file that you download is
an exe file I put that into my C bin
directory which is in my path and now
everything works okay so that's it and
then we just do this I don't yeah I
don't have make installed I mean it's
actually inside rib's installation cuz
it's inside this dev kit bin so I could
actually just add that to my path pretty
quick okay that did not work uh no taret
supposed no make file found that's a bit
weird cuz this this seemed to have
worked right and I put them here the
build files but then wouldn't I ninja
build it cuz I use ninja I think it
checks ninja first so I think I have to
like ninja it so this sub command failed
okay let's try em make ninja okay I
guess I can use that all right so what's
the problem here um failed o because of
what my little s my pral header but why
did that fail unsupported option Windows
oh is there something dodg inside my
cake yeah cuz I have this here so I
think this is where I'm kind of like I
need to make sure that I'm only doing
this for not like the web so I think
let's do I don't know what it is it's
not I'm pretty sure it's not Windows I
am not really a big cake user but I know
I need to do this this is Windows
specific I guess okay so let's try this
again cool that may have worked let's oh
no I thought it was done all right
everything failed awesome so this did
not work wait clang I thought I was
using GCC cuz it's I don't even know why
it's using that it should just be using
GCC right um I might just nuke this and
try again they actually created a make
file did we have a make file last time I
thought we didn't well we've got make
now anyway oh I actually just called it
okay sure but let's see what this does
okay uh that's actually pretty promising
um I think that's just this is not
included or something if defined
platform web I have a feeling we just
didn't never we never defined that but
like that this was defined though
actually yeah that doesn't make sense
this was defined from web so is it
specifically it might just be my weird
cuz that needs a callback function well
you know what this is actually a
Singleton anyway so cuz I think this is
a safe function so it might specifically
want us to do something like this in
which case because that's not we might
have to do static void Loop let's just
do this we can just do a normal Loop
here um and then we'll make static Loop
call Loop like that all right so GF W
doesn't look like it's being linked in
okay well this was lucky that we just
found this so I need to add this
apparently ifm scripton this seems like
a lot of stuff that just is not included
by this cake file that promises to
actually work so let's try
this um we're going to have to rerun
cmake though obviously yeah I'm
interested in I mean that's ignored
during use gfw is ignored during
compilation that sounds a bit not cool
all my basically all my Linker settings
are like ignored it's weird yeah so
compiling is fine but yeah linking is
not quite working mostly seems because
of g w whoa linking hey it worked
apparently so now we have a Genesis cb.
HTML file oh here it is did we do it
there's a JavaScript there's the web
assembly let's have a look pairing N Out
of n that's my favorite is that how far
we get yep maybe it's just missing some
stuff so access to that has been blocked
oh okay so I maybe have to deploy this
onto a server now let's quickly cut to
the Chase and talk about deployment
because if you're building this thing
for the web using rib you probably want
to be able to have it accessible by
everyone you know on the web now the RB
documentation actually has instructions
on how you can just deploy this on it IO
for free and that's a pretty good option
but if you want to deploy this on your
own server on your own VPS then let's
take a look at how we can do that using
hostinger the sponsor of this video let
me just start by saying that hostinger
has probably the best value web products
I've ever come across check out this VPS
KVM 2 plan for example it's quite
powerful super affordable and you can
also use coupon code Cho for an even
bigger discount server setup is a breeze
lots of operating systems to choose from
which is great after a quick 5 minute
setup you can just ssh in hosting gives
you full route access so you can do
whatever you need to do for this ra game
I already had an engine X server up and
running so I can just FTP all of my game
files over to the server and that's it
that's all it takes it's up and running
on Studio j/ Genesis hosting as high
performance servers use nvme ssds and
AMD epic processors for responsive
websites and web apps and they're easily
scalable which I love you can easily
change which plan you're on based on
your needs as you go and the benefits of
using hostinger don't stop there so head
on over to hosting.com Cho link will be
in the description below and use coupon
code chero for a limited time for an
additional discount on all you plans
thank you hostinger for sponsoring this
video I can do em run okay cool I'll do
that for now like just in here that
didn't didn't quite work exception
Throne failed to load resource favicon
why is it really just crash because of
the favon I don't think so it's probably
because of this right I mean it
initialized the audio device
successfully so like it did run some
stuff probably failed because it
couldn't load the audio or something he
didn't print that though it just crashed
cuz yeah that is a good point about like
external files and stuff how is it going
to read them oh here we go there's
something about resources failing to
load resource well it's actually not
saying that make sure you that you refer
to the resource directory in the same
way in the code and the and in the
preload file what's this preload file
thing oh create a data file well yeah
that's probably why okay preload file so
res that's the directory right so it
should give us a data file I think now
or something that just contains all the
packaged resources so that's this right
yeah Genesis c. dat which is 80 Meg so
that's probably the all the resources
now we did it course the music's not
playing though oh it is it just took
forever it's like popping a bit though
the audio could be the fact that we're
not actually running the music like the
update thing on a different thread could
be the like some kind of memory
limitation streams it differently or
whatever in the web version because of
I'm script and I don't know oh you know
what it would be extra annoying if I
specifically matched this color so
that's F7 a f yeah so let's copy this
that's actually so funny oh let's go
that is how we function here at Studio
Turner that's so
that's kind of cool though it's almost
looks like the game's actually full
screen are you guys enjoying me webding
cuz I'm not all right you guys who are
web devs here can you please help me cuz
I really don't want to spend time on
this garbage uh the problem is I don't
really quite want to Center this I kind
of want it to be aligned with the
beginning of the window or is that too
hard cuz then I kind of have to how
would I do that I'd probably actually I
probably could do that right probably
make a div that is cuz I know actually
know the width of this it's 900 right so
I probably could just make a div and if
I just set width to like 960 and then
does it have to be block hey I don't
need you I'm a web dev by the way quick
little side note quick little confession
guys I actually don't know what block
means I actually don't know what display
block is I know there's like different
like kinds of layout or alignment or
whatever on Earth but like can someone
please explain display block like I'm
you can put multiple in lines on a line
block means it takes the entire screen
width basically you seem board on the
yeah well look this is not my forte this
CSS HTML concoction I don't know what XX
large is see the web dev is just wild
like my font size I'd like it to be XX
large please imagine if that's like how
work yeah just XX large just that's the
font size bro what does that mean all
right I think we ship it okay I think
we're just going to put it on studio.com
yeah let's just grab all the and pop
them in there what do people use these
days for FTP cuz I feel like I've been
using file Zilla for like 20 years I
definitely want the icon sets I
definitely want the additional icons I
don't think I want to share my whole
server with you guys we're just not at
that stage in our relationship sorry
okay so this is this is what I made
Genesis so now I guess we just take this
I'm going to try to call this index else
hopefully that does blow blow up I don't
see why it would and then everything
else so I think this is all we need so
let's copy this across so now I guess we
just go to studio.com
Genesis and hopefully it'll work but it
probably won't hey we did it all right
everyone can now go to studio.com
Genesis and you can play Genesis without
even having to download it I should
probably renew my SSL certificates hold
your horses guys will have https in a
second just got to runer bot so good a
there we go okay never mind I guess it's
up okay and that's htps
now https and I don't know like to be
honest all of this really makes me kind
of appreciate Java a bit more just
because it was so much easier and like I
guess just the cool thing is having like
a jav file that you can just give
someone and literally they can run it on
Windows Mac and Linux but like if I want
this to run on Windows and L on Mac and
Linux I literally need to like build it
for those platforms separately and like
probably even on those platforms
potentially well maybe not with Linux
but I could probably do that on Windows
but I don't know about Mac I guess I
could probably build a Mac binary on
Windows is that a thing yeah if you guys
want to like try and build it yourselves
or like I don't know learn from it or
whatever on Earth The Cho / Genesis
remake on GitHub is where I just pushed
this right build web. bat here's the
batch file that does actually work and
then obviously all the adjustments and
everything um that I made you can look
at the diff if you want but it was just
kind of the static Loop thing and it
wasn't really much like to be honest
yeah good process better than I thought
it would be like a while ago when I was
working on Sparky like this was 2015 I
was making my little Sparky engine just
40 days before l or whatever I actually
compiled Sparky using M scripton for the
web as well but that was obviously not
like ra was kind of built with that in
mind obviously Sparky was my own engine
so I didn't really have any support for
that stuff you know I had to compile not
just Sparky for the web but all of the
dependencies including like I think I
was using like free image or something I
remember my boss like from EA was like
helping me do this like as then while I
was live streaming working on one thing
he'd be like trying to get free image I
think to build or whatever like it was
just it was hilarious um and it was very
very difficult so I just remember how
difficult that was yeah Sparky is
available on GitHub uh it's just the Cho
Sparky Sparky M scripton was much much
much harder obviously than ra BM script
and web build because it's basically set
up everything the hard work is done for
you you just have to actually build it I
hope you enjoyed this experience of
getting Genesis running on the web um
please just fix my AMD issues yes good
by